Rev. John Mack papers, 1921-2019. MS5555
Congregational Library & Archives
Rev. John Mack papers, 1921-2019.
Congregational Library & Archives
Mack, John (1942-2008)
Gerlach, Barbara
MS5555
4.06 Cubic Feet (5 boxes)
John Mack was born on March 7th, 1942, in New York City to Grace and Lewis Mack. He was the middle of three children and was raised in New Canaan, Connecticut. John attended Union Theological Seminary and received his Master of Divinity degree in 1971. While there, he met his future wife, Barbara Gerlach. In 1971, they would serve as co-pastors of Trinity Congregational UCC in Scranton, Pennsylvania. In 1984, John started to serve as the pastor of First Congregational Church in Washington, DC, and would spend the next 23 years there. While visiting the Himalayas in 2007, John fell ill and spent several weeks in the hospital. He died in his home, surrounded by his family, on January 15th, 2008. This collection contains materials both personal and profession from across John's life. Included are sermons, columns in Gabriel's Horn titled "A View from Here", other collected writings on numerous subjects, and personal files related to his friends and family.
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by Barbara Gerlach in June 2025; 2025-18.
Biographical Information
John Mack was born on March 7th, 1942, in New York City to Grace and Lewis Mack. He was the middle of three children and was raised in New Canaan, Connecticut. He attended Phillips Exeter Academy, Princeton University, and then served in Vietnam as an infantry officer in the Marine Corps from 1964-1967.
After returning home, John attended Union Theological Seminary and received his Master of Divinity degree in 1971. While there, he met his future wife, Barbara Gerlach. In 1971, they would serve as co-pastors of Trinity Congregational UCC in Scranton, Pennsylvania. They would move to Boston in 1973 when John was executive and clinical director of Together, Inc., a community outreach program that worked with at-risk teenagers and their families.
In 1984, John started to serve as the pastor of First Congregational Church in Washington, DC, and would spend the next 23 years there. During that time, the church became a just peace, open and affirming, multiracial and multicultural church, and in general a place for all walks of life in downtown Washington. Near the end of his tenure, John helped lead a process for developing the church's site into a mixed-use structure that houses the church and its social service programs, financed by eight floors of offices. John was also a member of the board of directors of the Downtown Cluster of Congregations from 1985-2007, which worked to develop a "lived-in" downtown during the 80s and 90s.
John's family included his wife Barbara, their two children Jessica Prentice and Peter Gerlach-Mack, several grandchildren, his sister Lucy Mack and brother Talbot Mack. While visiting the Himalayas in 2007, John fell ill and spent several weeks in the hospital. He died in his home, surrounded by his family, on January 15th, 2008.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials both personal and profession from across John's life. Included are sermons, columns in Gabriel's Horn titled "A View from Here", other collected writings on numerous subjects, and personal files related to his friends and family.
Arrangement
This collection was originally arranged and housed in three-ring binders by John's wife Barbara Gerlach. The material in those binders were removed into folders and kept in the same order. The collection is now arranged into 3 series and further arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Personal files, 1921-2019
Series 2: Sermons, 1971-2007
Series 3: Writings, 1983-2008
Technical Requirements
Contents of CD can be shared by asking an archivist while the files on the floppy drive are inaccessible.
Bibliography
Catalogue and biography, undated, in the Rev. John Mack papers, 1921-2019, MS5555. The Congregational Library & Archives, Boston, MA.
Christianity and politics.; Church group work.; Clergy -- Correspondence.; Human rights -- Religious aspects -- Congregational churches.; Letters.; Sermons, American.; Religious articles.; First Congregational Church (Washington, D.C.); Gerlach, Barbara; Mack, John (1942-2008)
- Personal files, 1921-2019; 12 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains personal files from John Mack and include vital records, material related to his family, his career, and his philanthropy. Also included are remebrances from his celebration of life by friends and family.
  - Personal files (1 of 2), 1921-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Personal files (2 of 2), 1921-1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Personal files (1 of 2), 1971-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Personal files (2 of 2), 1971-1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Personal files (1 of 2), 1984-1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Personal files (2 of 2), 1984-1995 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Personal files (1 of 2), 1984-2007 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Personal files (2 of 2), 1984-2007 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Personal files and remembrances (1 of 2), 2007-2012 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Personal files and remembrances (2 of 2), 2007-2012 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Celebration of the Life of John Hayward Mack, January 28, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 150th Anniversary of First Congregational Church of Washington DC, 2019 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Sermons, 1971-2007; 55 Folders
  This series contains sermons from across John's life, a majority of which come from the First Congregational Church of Washington DC but also includes sermons from his time at Trinity Congregational UCC in Scranton, Pennsylvania and the Church of the Covenant in Boston, Massachusetts.
  - Trinity Congregational Church UCC of Scranton, PA Sermons (1 of 2), 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Trinity Congregational Church UCC of Scranton, PA Sermons (2 of 2), 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Church of the Covenant in Boston, Mass, sermons, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sermons (1 of 3), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sermons (2 of 3), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sermons (3 of 3), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1997 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1997 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1999 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 2000 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 2001 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 2001 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 2002 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 2002 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Sermons (1 of 3), 2003 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sermons (2 of 3), 2003 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Sermons (3 of 3), 2003 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Sermons (1 of 3), 2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Sermons (2 of 3), 2004 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Sermons (3 of 3), 2004 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Sermons (1 of 3), 2005 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Sermons (2 of 3), 2005 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Sermons (3 of 3), 2005 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Sermons (1 of 3), 2006 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Sermons (2 of 3), 2006 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sermons (3 of 3), 2006 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sermons, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Writings, 1983-2008; 10 Folders
  This series contains various writings be John Mack, including articles he wrote in "Gabriel's Horn" titled "A View from Here", an unfinished novel, a catalogue and biography by his wife Barbara Gerlach, Christmas letters to friends and family, and other writings on various topics.
  - Gabriel's Horn, 1983-1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gabriel's Horn, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Gabriel's Horn, 1996-2000 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Gabriel's Horn, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Gabriel's Horn, 2001-2004 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Gabriel's Horn, 2005-2007 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Collected writings of John Mack, 1984-2008 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Novel, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Unfinished novel with outline and research, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Catalogue and biography, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)